<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Get! Set! Trade!</title>
    <description>Your resource to start trading sensibly</description>
    <link>https://ianmd.github.io/gst//gst/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://ianmd.github.io/gst//gst/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sat, 08 Sep 2018 23:22:05 -0700</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 08 Sep 2018 23:22:05 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.1.6</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Gearing up for a full time day trading career: 10 things you need to know</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;No career choices are easy as a beginner and day trading stocks is no exception. If you want to pursue a career in day trading, you have to make some tough choices in the beginning. Once you get your feet wet, you will have a better understanding of what you want from trading. Do not fall into the trap of making X amount of money in Y number of days. Just like any other acquired skill, this will take its own time. This list of 10 things will help you analyze how you can kickstart your day trading career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;1.Learn the basics&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regardless of how enthusiastic you may feel in the beginning, you will have to go through the learning curve. There are gazillion resources(link) online, available for free that you don’t need to spend a penny to learn any of these. However, buying a guided trading course(link) or a book(link) will speed up your process in getting there. If you take my advice, I would recommend learning on your own. Finding free resources on your own and the effort you put in doing that, has its own advantages. One of them is, you will get to know multiple point of views for the same topic. You will resonate to one of the views more than the rest and it will eventually help you to find your true niche as a day trader. One thing I would like to warn you is about multiple gurus who would show you dreams of achieving so much and end up looting your hard earned money. The only best way to spend your money for trading education is on commissions. More on that later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;2.Capital- Figure out how much you want to invest&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a no brainer that you need capital to become a day trader. However, no amount is right in the beginning. If you are in the US, you are stuck with the pattern day trading(PDT)(link) rule, which roughly translates to having a $25000 trading account to work as a day trader. But don’t be disappointed if you don’t have that much money. There are several options(link) if you still want to pursue this career. And the pattern day trading rule is good for you in the beginning. As a beginner day trader, you will have a myriad of emotions suppressing each other. One way or another, you will have bad emotions taking over the good ones, and those are the days PDT will help you from blowing up your account. If you are low on cash, you can get your feet wet in as low as $3000.  I would not recommend anyone with less than that capital to actively pursue this career. I’m not saying you will fail if you do that, but the odds of winning becomes slimmer as you go lower than that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;3.Scanning and Charting Software&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Day trading can be considered as running a small business. Like any other small business, you will have to bear some ongoing cost of running the business. In the beginning, however, you will not need to make a hole in your pocket by subscribing to various trading software. You should be fine with the one provided free by your broker(link). If you happen to have TD Ameritrade(link) as a broker, you will have access to thinkorswim(link). This is one of the best free resource you  can get as a beginner day trader. There is a very good community around this software and you will have to put very less effort to mould it to your liking. This will serve as a charting as well as basic scanner software. You may also look into free websites like Finviz or an awesome scanning software Trade Ideas for your scanner needs if you prefer. But in the beginning, the more simple your trading system is, the better you will get at learning things with sharp focus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;4.Do you need a specialized Trading Computer?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The simple answer is, no. Trading Computer is basically a computer with high processing power, support for multiple monitors, and larger RAM to run multiple operations at once. In my opinion, you are good with an average computer or even a laptop to begin. RAM of 4GB should be sufficient for most people, but I would recommend it to be 8GB. An addition of a second monitor will certainly help you organize necessary information, but any more than that is an overkill. At least, in the beginning. More number of monitors will only cause a distraction. It is very easy to be overwhelmed by the amount of information you will have to consume as a day trader. You don’t want to add to that in the beginning. Any money you would like to spend on a fancy computer system would be well utilized if just added to your capital. If you are a mac person, like I was, please don’t get furious if I tell you that the best way is to move to windows. I had to eventually make this tough choice as the emulators didn’t work good enough for me. I even installed windows for a couple of months but it didn’t work for me. I just didn’t like my macs once I had installed windows on them. Unfortunately, most of the trading platforms are designed and optimized for Windows systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further down the road, you will definitely need a good computer and a couple of monitors. If you want to buy a computer with the sole purpose of trading, you should look for any consumer grade gaming computers. They have all the processing power you need and support for multiple monitors. You can consider this one(link) as an example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;5.Amount of time you need to do trading&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is one of the most tricky part for a beginner trader. You’ll often hear that you need to be trading only 10 minutes or 2 hours or any other random time frame. This could be true once you’re a pronounced trader. In the beginning however, I would recommend to watch the market at different times. You will need to work your way out to find out which time frame will work best for you. You might also hear that don’t trade in the lunch hour, don’t trade afternoons etc. These are typically good advices, but you never know if those are the times you might feel comfortable to enter a position. Usually, for a beginner, the first opening 30 minutes could be very overwhelming. But some beginners do enjoy the adrenaline rush of the opening hour. There is no best time for anybody. I would highly recommend that you take the time to watch the market at different times, including pre market hours and after market hours. Don’t rush to take your positions. Just read the market for a little while.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &quot;Remember, Money is made by sitting, not trading.&quot;
  &lt;cite&gt;A Great Trader&lt;/cite&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;6.Is Paper Trading a good idea?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Depending on how you use paper trading, it could help you succeed or hurt you emotionally in the beginning. Usually, we tend to be careless about paper money and take unrealistic positions. This boosts our self confidence if we make big wins, however doesn’t hurt as much if we lose money. We carry those emotions to real trading eventually and find ourselves shooting in the foot. The best way to utilize paper trading is by a simple rule– Just treat paper money as it were real. By taking practical, small positions with paper money, you will not only learn how to control yourself, but also learn a great deal about viability to consider day trading as a career.With practical position sizes, you will be able to assess your potential profits or losses much better. One big difference between paper money account and real one is that you can’t analyze the fills. If you buy, for example,  a 100 shares of Apple Inc. at the price of $170.50, you will get total 100 shares in your account at that price. But, in a real account, this is rarely true. Since market fluctuates quickly, and there might not be enough number of shares available at the price you want, you might not get all the 100 shares you ordered at the price you wanted. This changes the complete math when you switch from paper trading to a real account. This doesn’t means that paper trading is useless, it’s just a good idea to get the facts straight. Ideally, your broker should provide you with free paper trading software. If that’s not the case, you will find a bunch of resources on the internet for this. As mentioned earlier, Thinkorswim is one of the best free resource out there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;7.Which Broker should you choose?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is obvious that you need a broker to start trading. However, many people waste so much time and energy in finding the best broker they can get. All you need is a broker with standard features like charting software and low commissions. For most brokers, commissions are comparable. However, be sure to read their terms regarding any potential hidden fees. Other than that, you don’t need to worry about anything else as a beginner trader. Further down the road, you might need to change your broker based on your style of trading, your choices of position sizing, your location etc. Whichever broker you pick, be sure to check out their educational resources. This will add a lot of quality content to your knowledge base.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;8.Training- Your true recipe for success&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the most important part of your trading career. To become a successful day trader, you need to have what I call an on job training. Just like when you start a business, you have to focus on the success of the business rather than making profit out of it from day one. You have to be willing to lose money in the beginning. As I mentioned earlier, I don’t want you to go and take some expensive chat room membership or enroll in a live trading program. You can do that by all means, but the best trading education you will get is by actually trading. I know it’s tempting to just jump in, and think about making a huge profit. But you need to take very small sizes and see if your thought process is working right. This does not mean you have to be right all the time, but merely means you have to slowly gauge if you are making the right decisions. Right decision is not the one that makes you profit all the time. Right decision is when you follow your rules, every time.  As you further your career as a day trader, you will find that following your own rules is one of the most challenging aspects of being successful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t think about justifying the commission for such a small position. That’s definitely going to be a loss, but you will learn a great deal from it. Once you get confident enough with your strategy, you will be able to raise your position sizes, eventually. As a beginner, be prepared to take some losses, sometimes in the form of commissions also.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;9.Strategise before you jump in&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will need to have a strategy to win in this career. I think all traders will unequivocally agree that they can’t enter a trade without a strategy. Trading without strategy is no different than gambling. A trading strategy is not some secret recipe to success from a trading guru. Rather, it’s very personal. You are supposed to strategize each trade exactly how you feel about it. You have to define for yourself when is the right time to enter a trade, position size, and when to make an exit. No one should tell you these three basic things. With experience, you will get so good at it that you will feel that screw all the rules, I make my own rules. There are some general concepts, however, that you need to follow. I’m not saying just blindly pick those three variables. You will learn the right time to enter and exit a trade from your trading education. The position size will depend on your account size etc. Bottom line is, you need to have a plan before taking each trade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &quot;Plan your trade, don&#39;t trade your plan&quot;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;10.Psychology: Setting up your brain for trading&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As they say, it’s all in the mind. All your wins and losses will be greatly affected by how you tackle your mental conflicts. There will be times, when your deepest gut feeling will stop you from doing the right thing. You will be bombarded with negative thoughts when you will need them the least. You might even not realize that how your emotions affect your trading decision. You have to spend a lot of time and effort to get your psychological strengths in place. Basically, you have to become a robot when it comes to trading. The more mechanical you can get, the better chances of success you have. Our brains are designed to protect us from taking risks and keep you in your comfort zone. It’s hard to not feel emotional whenever you make a win or a loss. But, it will take some time to learn that. It will not come naturally to you. Once you achieve that, your success will be just around the corner.   `&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://s6.postimg.cc/7q1v9db75/entrepreneur-3254525_1920.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Placeholder&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Launch Yourself&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s it, you are all set. If you keep your mindset open to learning trading, you will have one of the most rewarding and exciting careers. Remember, at no point you will feel that you know everything. From time to time, you will find about some new strategy that works for so on so person and a technical indicator which works magic. All you need to do is keep your eyes and ears open and not get stuck at anything. You are the architect of your own success, no one or nothing can tell you what will work best for you. Good luck.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 03 May 2018 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://ianmd.github.io/gst//gst/2018/05/03/Welcome-to-getsettrade/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ianmd.github.io/gst//gst/2018/05/03/Welcome-to-getsettrade/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Basics</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
